[Music]
skitso kitum the type of algae used to
make algae based DHA supplements is
grown under controlled conditions and
has been found to be free of marine
biotoxins the same can't be said for
blue green algae products like AFA
alphan men and floss aqu a blue green
algae harvested from clamo Lake in
Oregon and marketed as a dietary
supplement Studies have shown this blue
green algae can produce significant
levels of cylindrospermopsin and
saxitoxin cylindrospermopsin is a liver
Toxin and saxitoxin is a neurotoxin
listed as a schedule one substance in
the chemical weapons convention the
first big expose of AFA was published in
2000 with microsyst and liver toxins
found in 85 of 87 samples 72% an
exceeding Oregon State safety limits of
one part per million which is based on
an average adult weighing 60 kg about
132 lbs and consuming about 2 G A
Day AFA has the toxen genes that produce
these micro system directly but when
you're harvesting It Outdoors it's
almost impossible to avoid the presence
of other algae species that can produce
toxins too since they release on the
market and after some public inquiries
about adverse health effects of these
products the producers of the clamo lake
blue green algae products have
repeatedly claimed that their products
are safe well okay maybe not safe but at
least has toxin contamination below the
regulatory limit in 2018 dozens of blue
green algae products containing AFA were
tested and about a quarter were close to
or over the regulatory limit the only
one clth Lake powder significantly
exceeded the limit and nearly three
parts per million but in 2020 two AFA
supplements tested it closer to 50 parts
per million at the recommended doses
that could present up to 75 times the
tolerable daily intake when those two
off the-charts contaminated Brands were
tested in the 2018 survey they only had
down about the limit this confirms that
there's a potential for great
variability between lots of AFA
harvested from clouth Lake so even if a
supplement Company claims their brand
test under the limit you never know what
their next bottle is going to contain
other Studies have shown up to the same
50-fold variability among batches of the
very same brand they receiv receiving a
case report of a young woman who died of
liver failure tentatively attributed to
the prolonged consumption of toxic AFA
supplements given the levels of the
toxins the researchers were able to pick
up in the liver on autopsy in light of
the findings the distribution and
commercial sales of AFA blue green algae
products for human consumption
consumtion appear Highly Questionable
and the irony is that they're commonly
consumed for purported
detoxification here's the latest 2023
clth leg AFA continues to be
contaminated with up to 10 times the
upper safety limit to minimize exposure
to these toxins the researcher suggest
using spirulina or chlorella based
products
instead but are they any safer we'll
find out now next
[Music]